<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-22T22:41:45+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Modern Translation blog</title><subtitle>A blog focusing on the technical aspects of translation, such as scripting and software.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Getting started with Python</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/22/python-commandline-start.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting started with Python" /><published>2020-08-22T12:01:25+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-22T12:01:25+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/22/python-commandline-start</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/22/python-commandline-start.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repetitive tasks are exhausting to us humans. To computers, they are a breeze. So why should we be the ones doing them? With a tiny bit of scripting, we can make them the job of our machines!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Python, a programming language (named after Monty Python, not a snake). Beginner-friendly, readable and incredibly versatile. It allows you to automate and augment your workflows, letting you focus on the interesting parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will show you how to install Python, use it – both from the default launcher and Windows’ PowerShell – and customize some settings, making it easily accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. You have control over your computer&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;br /&gt;
   Seems obvious… but computers facing the general public, such as those in libraries, might have restricted access. Some options – e.g. installing Python – might not be available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Your operating system is Windows 10&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;br /&gt;
   The tutorial should also work on previous versions, but I can’t promise it does. Even if you have an older version, you can still try and give me some feedback if anything goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. You have Notepad, PowerShell and File Explorer&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
   If 2. is true for you, than this should be as well, since Windows has all these programs installed by default. Of course, if you prefer other programs and feel familiar with them, you can use them instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-installing-python&quot;&gt;1. Installing Python&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get Python, visit &lt;a href=&quot;www.python.org&quot;&gt;its website&lt;/a&gt;. It should automatically offer the Python version most suited for your operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you download it, you should have a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python-&amp;lt;x.y.z&amp;gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt; file, where &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;x.y.z&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; will be your version number. Click on it to launch the installer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tcl/tk and IDLE&lt;/code&gt; option is selected on the first screen (IDLE is the editor we’re going to use).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/pyinstall1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you reach the second screen, make sure &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Add Python to environment variables&lt;/code&gt; is selected. This option will allow you to call Python from any folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/pyinstall2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest is up to you, you can stick to the default options, although I &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; recommend choosing the &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt; option from the first screen as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;If you have already installed Python without choosing the options I recommend, you can still click the &lt;em&gt;.exe&lt;/em&gt; file again, select the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Modify...&lt;/code&gt; option and choose them; no need to reinstall the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is a &lt;em&gt;programming language&lt;/em&gt;, which means that it’s just a set of logical rules; it has no physical form of its own and has to be launched &lt;strong&gt;inside another program&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launcher installed by default is called IDLE. It’s simple but sweet. And specifically tailored to Python, so it &lt;em&gt;understands it&lt;/em&gt; and can offer some helpful features (e.g. applying different text color to commands which have a special meaning in Python).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s try it out! You can open IDLE from the start menu, under the &lt;em&gt;Python&lt;/em&gt; tab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/python_in_startmenu.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will see Python’s &lt;strong&gt;interactive shell&lt;/strong&gt;, a place where you can enter Python commands and see your results right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/python_hello.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type in (or copy and paste after the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) the text below, then confirm by pressing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Hello!'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be displayed in blue and the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; prompt will jump to the next line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/python_hello2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meaning that your Python is working!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-creating-your-first-script&quot;&gt;2. Creating your first script&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python’s interactive mode is useful for poking around, but it doesn’t store any commands between sessions. You usually want to prepare some functions beforehand, save them somewhere on your disk and then load them when you need them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; files are used for. We will create and save our first Python script, using IDLE’s editor mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;Python’s &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; files are simple text files; if you wanted, you could create them in Notepad as well and save with the &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; extension. We are only using IDLE’s editor for convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without leaving IDLE, open the script editor (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ctrl&lt;/code&gt;+&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;File &amp;gt; New file&lt;/code&gt; from the top left menu). You will see an empty window similar to Notepad. This is where you can write Python files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s write something to test our script, like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Hello from script!'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/hello_untitled.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s run the script. Press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;F5&lt;/em&gt;. A prompt will appear asking you to save the file first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/src_must_be_saved.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose OK to open the standard file saving window. I have created a new folder, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\MyScripts&lt;/code&gt;, which I will also use as my future folder for Python scripts. If you want to follow the tutorial to the letter, do the same; you can also add any other name you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the bottom field, enter the name you want to give to your Python file and confirm (I used &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;myscript&lt;/code&gt;). You don’t have to type in the &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; extension, it will be added automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IDLE’s interactive mode will be launched and you should see your text, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Hello from script!&lt;/code&gt;, printed in blue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/hello_from_script_result.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it works, it means that you can now write helpful scripts and place them in any folders you want!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to reach Python from anywhere, not just by opening its scripts. For this, we’ll use the default utility bundled with Windows – PowerShell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-python-in-powershell&quot;&gt;3. Python in PowerShell&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put: PowerShell is a minimalistic (text-only, no graphical gimmicks) tool for launching other programs. You can – and usually will – launch it from your File Explorer. Open it from the top menu, after clicking the dark-blue &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;File&lt;/code&gt; tab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/powershell_open.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trick:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you use the File Explorer, you can also hold the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Shift&lt;/code&gt; button and right-click anywhere with the mouse; you will see the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Open PowerShell here&lt;/code&gt; option in the popup menu, which is normally hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click the option to open PowerShell. It has this minimalistic look, like from all the mainstream hacker movies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/powershell_first_launch.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first two letters, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PS&lt;/code&gt;, indicate that it’s PowerShell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then you have the currently active directory – the folder “you are currently in”. It’s &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\Examples\Python_first_steps&lt;/code&gt; in my case.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In PowerShell, &lt;strong&gt;active directory matters&lt;/strong&gt;. Alot. In Python’s case, it usually matters when you &lt;em&gt;import&lt;/em&gt; files, meaning that you load the code contained inside them. By default, you can only call your ad-hoc scripts from the same folder where you put them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The last part is the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; sign and a blinking cursor after it. This is where you can type commands; there are many of them available and they don’t have to be related to Python at all!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s check if we can reach Python from anywhere. Type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; and confirm with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;. You should see the same familiar mode as in IDLE, but less colorful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/powershell_python.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Travel analogy&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
Imagine Python is a travelling artist. Python has great potential, but in order to create anything, he/she has to get some personal space first. IDLE and PowerShell are two of many places which can host our traveller and provide this space.&lt;br /&gt;
IDLE is like the house of Python’s distant relative. The host knows Python well and adjusts decorations to our artist’s preferences (&lt;em&gt;syntax highlighting&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;
PowerShell is like a large hotel. It can accept many different guests, so Python has to check in before getting a room (hence we have to type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python&lt;/code&gt;). It also does not cater to Python’s specific tastes (&lt;em&gt;no highlighting&lt;/em&gt;), but has some general useful facilities (like &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;autocompletion&lt;/em&gt;, not discussed here).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s stop for a bit and imagine the potential. What if, in the future, we could just move to a folder with the files we need to translate, open PowerShell, type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python do_my_job&lt;/code&gt; and see all boring parts done before our eyes? Just enough to aid us without making us redundant of course ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This future might not be that far, but we have to lay some more foundation and customize our settings a bit. Don’t close PowerShell yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;customizations&quot;&gt;Customizations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-locating-pythons-source-folder&quot;&gt;4. Locating Python’s source folder&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be playing around with some of Python’s settings now. To do it, we should get to its core folder, buried deep within the files. There are many ways to find it… but since we have Python open in PowerShell, we might as well use it to show us the path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, with Python still active in PowerShell, type (or copy from here):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import sys&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confirm by pressing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;. You should receive no visual feedback – apart from the console jumping to the next line – but trust me, all we needed has been loaded. Now type or copy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;for p in sys.path: print(p)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;twice&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the result we should see (one of the paths highlighted by me; of course, your user name will also be different):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/sys_path.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;If you want to know what’s happening: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sys.path&lt;/code&gt; belongs to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sys&lt;/code&gt; module we’ve imported. It’s a list of paths where Python searches for its scripts. By using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;for...&lt;/code&gt;, we move through its elements one by one. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; is just a temporary name given to each of these elements. And we use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;print&lt;/code&gt;, because we want each path in a form we can easily copy. If we hadn’t used it, we would e.g. have double slashes (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\&lt;/code&gt;) instead of single ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copy the path ending with &lt;em&gt;lib&lt;/em&gt;, which I’ve highlighted in the picture above. This is where Python stores its files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then open File Explorer and click on the right side of the address bar (marked in red):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/file_selection_window.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will select the whole path as text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/file_selection_window2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paste the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;...\lib&lt;/code&gt; path you’ve copied from PowerShell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/file_selection_window3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and confirm by pressing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext kbd highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;. You are now inside Python’s main folder. This is what you should see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/python_lib_dir.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have marked two folders which are of interest to us. We will work on them during the next two steps, so don’t close this Explorer window yet. I’ll be referring to it as the &lt;strong&gt;Python folder window&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-making-idle-open-py-files-by-default&quot;&gt;5. Making IDLE open &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; files by default&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; files get &lt;strong&gt;launched&lt;/strong&gt; when you double-click them. Not much happens – you catch a glimpse of a dark console window when the code inside gets executed, then it disappears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to open a file for &lt;strong&gt;editing&lt;/strong&gt;, you can right-click its name, select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Edit with IDLE&lt;/code&gt;, and then choose the option to the right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/open_with_idle_option.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But right-clicking and selecting is rather slow. If (when!) we get addicted to Python, we will be editing files often, so let’s make it as ergonomic as we can. Let’s make IDLE open the file in edit mode after a double left click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right-click on any &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; file, then select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Open with&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
You will see a list of programs which could be used to open the file. Unfortunately, IDLE is not on it. Click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;More apps&lt;/code&gt; and also &lt;strong&gt;the box next to the “Always use…” option&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/open_with_menu.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IDLE’s still not there. Scroll down to the end of the list and click the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Look for another app on this PC&lt;/code&gt; option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/py_more_options.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A File Explorer window will appear, from which you can choose any file we want. I’ll call it &lt;strong&gt;IDLE selection window&lt;/strong&gt; for now. Don’t close it, we’ll get back to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want the path to our IDLE, which is buried surprisingly deep in the files! To get it, open the &lt;strong&gt;Python folder window&lt;/strong&gt; from before. There, copy the path from the upper bar (using the same steps as in the previous point).&lt;br /&gt;
Move back to the &lt;strong&gt;IDLE selection window&lt;/strong&gt; and click on the right side of the filepath bar, like before. Paste the path you copied and confirm. You will move to Python’s main directory. Move to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;idlelib&lt;/code&gt; folder, where IDLE is stored. There, you can select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;idle.bat&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/file_selection_window4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confirm. The Python file you originally clicked should open in IDLE, ready for editing. Well done! From now on, you can open all &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt; files with a double left-click. Making quick changes to your scripts will be quick and smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I’d like to give credit to &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/24988880/set-python-idle-as-default-program-to-open-py-extensions&quot;&gt;this great answer from StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt;, which showed me where to look for IDLE!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-creating-a-folder-for-your-python-scripts&quot;&gt;6. Creating a folder for your Python scripts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, you can create your own scripts and launch Python from anywhere…  but how about calling &lt;strong&gt;your own scripts from anywhere&lt;/strong&gt;? Let’s create a separate folder for all the scripts we make ourselves. This way, we can easily launch them, organise them and move them between computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, we have to create a separate folder and “let Python know” that it should also look inside it whenever we try to import files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can create this folder in any location. In my case, I used the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\\PyScripts&lt;/code&gt; folder created in step 2. Inside it, I put a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;myscript.py&lt;/code&gt; file, which only contains &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;print('Hello from anywhere!')&lt;/code&gt; and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the &lt;strong&gt;Python folder window&lt;/strong&gt; from before, where I’ve marked two subfolders? One of them is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site_packages&lt;/code&gt;. It’s the place where Python looks for scripts to import. We can also put paths to our custom folders inside it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open this &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site_packages&lt;/code&gt; folder and create a new text file by e.g. right-clicking and selecting &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;New &amp;gt; Text Document&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;The file can have any name, but must end with the .pth extension&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/3402168/permanently-add-a-directory-to-pythonpath&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then open the file with Notepad (right-click, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Open with...&lt;/code&gt;). Inside it, enter the path to the custom folder you’ve created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/myscripts_pth_file.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s test it out! Using File Explorer, move to ANY location and open PowerShell. Inside it, type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; to enter the interactive mode. And then type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import x&lt;/code&gt;, putting the name of your file (without &lt;em&gt;.py&lt;/em&gt;) instead of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt;. Confirm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/hello_anywhere.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the first line – it shows that I’m calling PowerShell from the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;D:\&lt;/code&gt; location. And yet, when I import a Python script called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;myscript.py&lt;/code&gt; located somewhere else (in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\MyScripts&lt;/code&gt;), it still works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;If you wanted, you could also avoid creating your own folder and simply put your scripts in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site_packages&lt;/code&gt; – they would still be accessible from anywhere. But as you download more Python packages, it’s easy to forget which scripts are yours or, even worse, to accidentally overwrite them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6b-pinning-your-script-folder-in-explorer&quot;&gt;6b. Pinning your script folder in Explorer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to go the extra mile (well, maybe more of a meter…), you can also add pin your Python folder to File Explorer’s sidebar. To do this, simply right click on it in File Explorer and select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext win highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Pin to Quick access&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as you move around the files in Explorer, it will always be visible to your left, one click away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost3_python_first_steps/quickpin.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;7-python-from-everywhere-in-one-line&quot;&gt;7. Python from everywhere, in one line&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is more of a demonstration than a customization. If you completed the previous step and importing works, you can open a new PowerShell window anywhere and type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python -m myscript&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…replacing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;myscript&lt;/code&gt; with the name of the script you’ve imported before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-m&lt;/code&gt; is a so-called &lt;strong&gt;flag&lt;/strong&gt; which indicates that we want to launch a specific script instead of Python in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…And sure enough, when we confirm, it does print our “Hello from anywhere”. We can directly call all Python scripts from our custom folder this way. A single line is enough to reach Python from anywhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this tutorial, you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have a working version of Python on your computer;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can launch Python from any folder on your computer, using PowerShell;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can create and save Python scripts for further use;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have a folder where you can place all your Python scripts to make them accessible from anywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some example workflows now available to you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creating a single-use script:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;When you want a one-time “fire and forget” script to prepare a single set of files, you can quickly make a new one, refine it, launch it… And then leave it alone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using custom scripts regularly&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes you find out that your jobs involve repeating steps and you come to the decision to “promote” some of your scripts to regular ones. In this case, you can just copy them to your custom folder and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; their contents from anywhere, to use it in future situations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Making changes to existing scripts&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;You can swiftly edit your scripts by double-clicking them and making changes in IDLE.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Migrating to a new computer&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;When you are moving to a different machine and want to keep your collection of Python scripts, you can just copy your custom folder, move it, and then, on your new machine, create a &lt;em&gt;.pth&lt;/em&gt; file pointing to its path. With all scripts in one place, you don’t risk forgetting anything.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I day-dreamt in point 3 about calling Python to do a large part of our jobs? Turns out we can’t solve everything by typing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python do_my_job&lt;/code&gt;… It’s actually &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext pshell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python -m do_my_job&lt;/code&gt; ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future posts, I will share some ideas for what this mythical &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;do_my_job&lt;/code&gt; could be – I will review some example scripts and show when they could be useful. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">File formats in CAT tools 2 – direct editing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/16/translation-formats-practice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="File formats in CAT tools 2 – direct editing" /><published>2020-08-16T13:50:25+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-16T13:50:25+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/16/translation-formats-practice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/16/translation-formats-practice.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a series of blog posts on file formats used by CAT (Computer-assisted translation) programs for storing translation data. Their aim is to share some knowledge which should allow us to tame our CAT tools better. Or to become independent from their whims.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post discusses ways of editing file types often used by translators – XML files and archives – without actually using a CAT tool. If you want to learn about these filetypes first, see &lt;a href=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/intro/files/xml/2020/05/11/translation-formats-intro.html&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, things are simple: you get a file (&lt;em&gt;translation package&lt;/em&gt;) for translation, you open it with a specified CAT tool. It opens easily, you translate it and send it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are many reasons you may want to stray from the path and work with the files on your own terms. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You want to use your preferred CAT tool, but it does not directly support the format of the translation package.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.proz.com/forum/sdl_trados_support/211489-how_to_work_on_a_xlz_file.html&quot;&gt;Example 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.proz.com/forum/sdl_trados_support/344630-using_lionbridge_files_in_trados_2015_ok_reverting_back_lionbridge_says_not_ok.html&quot;&gt;example 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.sdl.com/product-groups/translationproductivity/f/studio/6040/working-with-xyleme-xlz-packages&quot;&gt;example 3&lt;/a&gt; and perhaps many others…)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t need the full content of translation packages and only want to get specific files (e.g. glossaries) out of them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You want to change the status of some segments before loading them into your CAT tool.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;E.g. they might have been accidentally locked, so you can’t edit them, but you have to… Oh, and you don’t have time to wait for the agency to send a new version!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After you finish your work, you are asked for some light find-and-replace corrections.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;But you are still traumatised by the CAT tool you were forced to use, and you don’t want to see it ever again…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Countless other reasons!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what reason you may have, &lt;strong&gt;you should be free to work with files in the way which is most comfortable to you&lt;/strong&gt;. If CAT tools make you face obstacles, you can bend them to your will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to play with translation files, you only need a few programs bundled with Windows by default:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;File Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (installed by default on all Windows versions; however, the one I use is bundled with Windows 10 and I don’t know if older ones support zip files);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;text editor&lt;/strong&gt; for opening files (on Windows, you can use the default Notepad or the free &lt;a href=&quot;https://notepad-plus-plus.org/&quot;&gt;Notepad++&lt;/a&gt;; larger office suites, such as LibreOffice or Microsoft Word, are also OK);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(optional, but helpful) any &lt;strong&gt;web browser&lt;/strong&gt;: Firefox, Brave, Edge, maybe even Chrome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want, you can also use a CAT tool compatible with the translation package format to check if the edited package opens correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow my example, find and download &lt;strong&gt;Idiom WorldServer&lt;/strong&gt; and then get the &lt;em&gt;.xlz&lt;/em&gt; package it uses for its tutorial.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Sidenote:&lt;/strong&gt; I chose Idiom’s file, because I had some trouble finding any other &lt;em&gt;.xlz&lt;/em&gt; packages on the web (though I know that the format is rather popular). For the purpose of future posts, I will probably upload a minimal file of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stage-1-unpacking&quot;&gt;Stage 1: Unpacking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this example, I use a translation package in the form of a zipped archive – an &lt;em&gt;.xlz&lt;/em&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: this format is used by the two clunkiest, most unpleasant CAT tools I have used in my life: Idiom WorldServer and Lionbridge’s TMS. For this reason, cracking this filetype is a way for me to confront the ghosts of the past :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bit of overview: .xlz files are actually archive files. They contain an &lt;em&gt;.xlf&lt;/em&gt; file, which is based on XML and the one we directly translate; there can also be an &lt;em&gt;.skl&lt;/em&gt; (skeleton) file describing the original structure, and other supplementary files, such as glossaries (also XML-based, usually with the &lt;em&gt;.tbx&lt;/em&gt; extension).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;If you want a primer on archives and XML files, check out &lt;a href=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/intro/files/xml/2020/05/11/translation-formats-intro.html&quot;&gt;the previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s get to the action! First, place the copy of the file in some separate directory. I personally use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C://Examples&lt;/code&gt; in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to extract the files from the zip archive. However, unless you have some specific software installed, our File Explorer does not recognize the &lt;em&gt;.xlz&lt;/em&gt; extension as an archive and does not give us the option directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could use a zip-handling program here, such as 7Zip, to forcefully extract the files (I normally do, so my icon for the &lt;em&gt;.xlz&lt;/em&gt; filetype has a &lt;em&gt;7Z&lt;/em&gt; on it).&lt;br /&gt;
Luckily, we don’t have to – default Windows tools can also help us, but we have to convince them that this mysterious file is actually a zip archive. How? By renaming it to &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rename the file, either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;right-click on its name and select the &lt;em&gt;Rename&lt;/em&gt; option from the popup menu, &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;left-click the name and choose the &lt;em&gt;Rename&lt;/em&gt; option from the upper menu (under the &lt;em&gt;File&lt;/em&gt; tab).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have marked both options below, using red boxes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/file_rename.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The fast way:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can also left-click the filename and press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;F2&lt;/em&gt; to start renaming!&lt;br /&gt;
Then, you can press &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; arrow key (to deselect the name) and then the &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;End&lt;/em&gt; key (to jump to the end, after the extension).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal trick here is that I don’t &lt;em&gt;replace&lt;/em&gt; the extension with &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt;, but rather &lt;strong&gt;add it&lt;/strong&gt; to the end, getting &lt;em&gt;.xlz.zip&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a bit faster for a keyboard-based workflow… And, if I have to take a break in the middle of my work, I don’t have to remember what the original extension was – it just stays there in the name :p&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type the &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt; extension and press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/em&gt; to confirm. A warning prompt appears:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/file_rename_warning.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds scary, but don’t worry! Like I mentioned in the first blog post, changing the extension does not change the file contents themselves. Click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/code&gt; or press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/em&gt; again.&lt;br /&gt;
After renaming, the file icon should change to that of a zip archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s not the only thing that’s changed! If you double-click on the zip file, you will see the files inside as if it were a normal folder. The only indication is the file path, which ends with &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Also take a look at the top menu. A new tab, &lt;em&gt;Compressed Folder Tools&lt;/em&gt;, has appeared! To extract the files, do the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Left-click the &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt; file (if you are not “inside” it);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;click the &lt;em&gt;Compressed Folder Tools&lt;/em&gt; tab;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and then the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Extract all&lt;/code&gt; option on the right-hand side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/zip_extraction_steps.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dialog box will appear, asking us about the folder we want to extract the files to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/file_extraction_popup.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the folder will have the same name as the zip archive, just without the &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt; extension. In my case, since I had the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;idiom_tutorial_copy.xlz.zip&lt;/code&gt; file in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C://Examples&lt;/code&gt;, the path offered to me by default is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C://Examples/idiom_tutorial_copy.xlz&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fine by me, let’s use this path! Click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/code&gt; or press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/em&gt;. We now have our original zip archive and a folder with its contents, right next to it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/after_extraction.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Interestingly, the folder has the &lt;em&gt;.xlz&lt;/em&gt; extension, but the icon of a folder… and it acts like one as well! This is because the &lt;em&gt;file vs folder&lt;/em&gt; distinction is contained in the metadata, and not influenced by any extensions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your only goal was to get some files out of the package, then you can just copy them out and finish right here :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stage-2-modifying&quot;&gt;Stage 2: Modifying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the archive is unpacked, we have a bunch of XML files (&lt;em&gt;.xlf&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;.tbx&lt;/em&gt; and plain &lt;em&gt;.xml&lt;/em&gt;). And these are perfectly editable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/unpacking_results.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When browsing popular discussion boards for translators, I’ve seen many different cases of people editing XML directly, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;removing the &lt;em&gt;machine-translated&lt;/em&gt; tag from Trados’ &lt;em&gt;.sdlxliff&lt;/em&gt; files;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changing the languages codes within a translation memory file if the current ones are not recognized by the CAT tool (e.g. &lt;em&gt;EN&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;EN-GB&lt;/em&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;anonymizing the file (removing personal data).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the use-cases seem interesting, but perhaps the last one is the one we could all benefit from. Therefore, I will make it the focus of my example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The file I want to edit is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;eGate Project for DWB Tutorial_tasks.xlf&lt;/code&gt;, because it contains the actual source-translation pairs. This is where translators’ personal data can be stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browsing the file with Notepad would be a pain, since it shows its contents as a single, huge, black-and-white block of text.&lt;br /&gt;
A better text editor would be great here… this is why I recommend Notepad++ for Windows users. But you have to download it from the Internet. Isn’t there something included on all PCs, which would allow us to view XML in a pleasant way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I mention &lt;em&gt;the Internet&lt;/em&gt;? Actually, almost all PCs have a tool whose job is to constantly parse HTML files, which are very similar to XML. Yep, these are &lt;strong&gt;our web browsers&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can open the &lt;em&gt;.xlf&lt;/em&gt; file with the browser (e.g by right-clicking the file, then selecting &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Open with&lt;/code&gt; and choosing a browser, Firefox in my case). We will see its structure in all its glory, with indendation and highlights!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browsers have one weakness though – although they are good at &lt;strong&gt;displaying&lt;/strong&gt; XML, they are by default not suitable for &lt;strong&gt;editing&lt;/strong&gt; it. You could of course open the developer tools or download some extension… seems fun, but this is out of my league, and I also want to stick to the basics ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, let’s use both tools together, by using the browser for viewing and the Notepad for replacing text! Here, I have put them both side by side:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/notepad_browser_compare.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By your powers combined…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While skimming the document in Firefox, I notice that some of the tags have attributes related to a company (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;company-name=&quot;Idiom&quot;&lt;/code&gt;) and to a translator (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;contact-name=&quot;Tom Translator&quot;&lt;/code&gt;). Let’s say that we don’t want them in the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we click on the Notepad window, press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Ctrl&lt;/em&gt;+&lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt; to get the replacement popup. We put:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Tom Translator&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;Find&lt;/em&gt; field;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Anonymous&lt;/code&gt; (or any other name) in the &lt;em&gt;Replace&lt;/em&gt; field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/replace_window.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Replace All&lt;/code&gt;. All mentions of the translator should disappear. After we are done, we can save (&lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Ctrl&lt;/em&gt;+&lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;) the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The replacements were safe in this case, but normally it’s better not to treat XML like plain text, or at least to be careful. Although XML files can be readable, they are more structured and reckless edits (like replacing the “ character, which has special meaning) could corrupt the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stage-3-repackaging&quot;&gt;Stage 3: Repackaging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we are done with changing the files, we may want to put them back into the translation package. In this case, just make sure they are all in the same folder and then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;select them (you can press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Ctrl&lt;/em&gt;+&lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; in File Explorer);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;select the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Share&lt;/code&gt; tab from the upper menu;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Zip&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/zipping_back_steps.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you zip the files, the name of the resulting zip archive will be highlighted automatically, allowing you to easily change it. One caveat though – by default, the zipped folder has the same name as the &lt;strong&gt;first of the files&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/initial_rename.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…And we want it to have the same name as &lt;strong&gt;the folder which contained the files&lt;/strong&gt;. Luckily, if we added the &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt; extension at the very end, we can get the right name name easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the bar above, where you have the full path to the file. Then left-click between the current folder name and the arrow icon (zone marked in red):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/adr_bar1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path will be selected in text form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/adr_bar2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now use your mouse/keyboard to select the last part (in my case, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;idiom_tutorial_copy.xlz&lt;/code&gt;), copy it and insert as the name of the zip file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The fast way&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
After selecting, copy with &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Ctrl&lt;/em&gt;+&lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;. Then left-click on the zipped folder, press &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;F2&lt;/em&gt; to enter the rename mode, &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Ctrl&lt;/em&gt;+&lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; to select all text, &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Ctrl&lt;/em&gt;+&lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;V&lt;/em&gt; to replace it with the copied name. Then confirm with two &lt;em class=&quot;kbd&quot;&gt;Enter&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excellent, now we have the modified files inside the zipped file, named the same way as the original package!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost2/final_look.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can copy this package and either put it into an actual CAT tool for further processing or send it to our client in exchange for $$$ if our modifications were only some finishing touches :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Instead of selecting the files and zipping them, you might feel tempted to zip the whole folder, so that it gets the name you want right away. &lt;strong&gt;DON’T&lt;/strong&gt;! If you do this, your package will become one level deeper (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;zip archive &amp;gt; folder &amp;gt; files&lt;/code&gt; instead of the original &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;zip archive &amp;gt; files&lt;/code&gt;) and CAT tools might not be able to open it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have discussed in detail a rather popular workflow which allows you to get some files out of translation packages and modify them before they are loaded into a CAT tool… or to bypass the CAT tool altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantage of this workflow is that it does not require any special software, you can simply use the applications already installed by default on most Windows PCs (and probably on other systems as well – I can only speak for Linux Mint here!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its disadvantage is that it requires some mouse-clicking, typing and opening programs every time you want to work with a translation package. For this reason, it’s not suited for tasks where you have to modify multiple packages. Sure, you can learn keyboard shortcuts, train your muscle memory etc., but you will eventually hit a wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with a little bit of scripting, we can easily break this wall down and handle any number of zipped packages! This is what the next post in this series will be about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, have fun handling your packages in creative ways! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a series of blog posts on file formats used by CAT (Computer-assisted translation) programs for storing translation data. Their aim is to share some knowledge which should allow us to tame our CAT tools better. Or to become independent from their whims.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">File formats in CAT tools 1 - a gentle introduction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/intro/files/xml/2020/05/11/translation-formats-intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="File formats in CAT tools 1 - a gentle introduction" /><published>2020-05-11T13:50:25+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-11T13:50:25+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/intro/files/xml/2020/05/11/translation-formats-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/modern_translation_blog/intro/files/xml/2020/05/11/translation-formats-intro.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a series of blog posts on file formats used by CAT (Computer-assisted translation) programs for storing translation data. Their aim is to share some knowledge which should allow us to tame our CAT tools better. Or to become independent from their whims.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post discusses some basic facts related to XML and archive files. If you want to jump straight to editing them without a CAT tool, see &lt;a href=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/16/translation-formats-practice.html&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;common-formats-used-in-translation&quot;&gt;Common formats used in translation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many programs for computer-aided translation use their custom file extensions: MemoQ’s &lt;em&gt;.mqxliff&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;.mqxlz&lt;/em&gt;, Trados’ &lt;em&gt;.sdlxliff&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;.sdlproj&lt;/em&gt;, the interoperable &lt;em&gt;.tmx&lt;/em&gt;… This variety gives some translators the feeling that the files might be tied to the respective software and that they cannot be edited in other ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, that is not the case. Most of the time, we can access and modify the content of these files. Even without using any CAT tools. In this post, I will try to untangle some myths related to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I will only focus on intermediate formats used directly by CAT tools. File formats we can import &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; our CATs (such as &lt;em&gt;.docx&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;.pdf&lt;/em&gt;) will only be briefly mentioned. They have their own quirks and I will discuss them in separate posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, we can divide most of file formats used by translation software into two categories: &lt;strong&gt;XML files&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;archives&lt;/strong&gt;. The table below contains a summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;general&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Trados&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;MemoQ&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XML file&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Can be opened with a text editor)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;.tmx&lt;br /&gt;.tbx&lt;br /&gt;.xliff&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;.sdlxliff&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;.mqxliff&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Archive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Has to be decompressed)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;.xlz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;.sdlppx&lt;br /&gt;.sdlrpx&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;.mqxlz&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s discuss the two basic types in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;xml-files&quot;&gt;XML files&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XML (eXtensible Markup Language) is an incredibly widespread format for storing data and the basis of countless applications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configuration data of Android apps? XML.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Format for financial statements? XBRL, based on XML.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vector graphics? SVG, based on XML.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geolocation data? Often XML.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many things in the world were built atop some tailored XML 😀 It has also become the most popular intermediate format for translation files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As translators, we might be using a few kinds of XML-based formats or their derivatives: &lt;em&gt;.xliff&lt;/em&gt; (for storing source-target pairs), &lt;em&gt;.tmx&lt;/em&gt; (for translation memories) or &lt;em&gt;.tbx&lt;/em&gt; (for glossaries).&lt;br /&gt;
Custom formats, &lt;em&gt;.mqxliff&lt;/em&gt; from MemoQ and &lt;em&gt;.sdlxliff&lt;/em&gt; from Trados, are based on &lt;em&gt;.xliff&lt;/em&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of XLIFF file content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot; data-lang=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;xliff&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;xmlns=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;urn:oasis:names:tc:xliff:document:2.0&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;version=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;2.0&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;srcLang=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;en-US&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;trgLang=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;ja-JP&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;f1&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;original=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Graphic Example.psd&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;skeleton&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Graphic Example.psd.skl&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!--The 1st translation unit, containing source and target.--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;unit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;segment&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;source&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;XLIFF Data Manager&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/source&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;target&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;XLIFF データ・マネージャ&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/target&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/segment&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/unit&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!--Potentially more units...--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/file&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/xliff&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Example adopted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XLIFF&quot;&gt;the Wikipedia entry on XLIFF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some XML basics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most notable part of XML structure are &lt;strong&gt;tags&lt;/strong&gt;. We can distinguish between start (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;...&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) and end (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/...&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) tags.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first string of characters within the brackets (before whitespace) is the &lt;strong&gt;name&lt;/strong&gt; of the tag.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A pair of same-name tags and everything between them (text, other tags etc.) is called an &lt;strong&gt;element&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s the basic building block of XML. Elements can be nested in each other.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;segment&lt;/code&gt; element (lines 9-12). Its start tag is &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;segment&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt; and the end tag is &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;/segment&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt;). It is contained in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unit&lt;/code&gt; element. It also contains two child elements: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;target&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apart from the obligatory name, each element may contain &lt;strong&gt;attributes&lt;/strong&gt;, which have some specific &lt;strong&gt;values&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They may only be specified in the start tag. The end tag contains the name only.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In this case, the attributes of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;file&lt;/code&gt; element (line 4) are &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;original&lt;/em&gt;. The value of the &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt; attribute is &lt;em&gt;&quot;f1&quot;&lt;/em&gt;. The value of the &lt;em&gt;original&lt;/em&gt; attribute is &lt;em&gt;&quot;Graphic Example.psd&quot;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tag pairs without other content between them can also be written as a single tag, with a forward slash at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In our case, it’s the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;skeleton (...) /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag from line 5. It could have also been written as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;skeleton (...)&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/skeleton&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space between elements does not matter that much. The example was indented (&lt;em&gt;prettified&lt;/em&gt;) for clarity, but the tags could have also been put in one line, one right after the other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is most interesting to us, as translators, are the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;target&lt;/code&gt; elements. They occur in many different bi- or multilingual files. The first type contains the original text, and the second one contains the translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;archives&quot;&gt;Archives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archives are basically compressed folders which can contain multiple files. They might have different extensions, but in many cases &lt;strong&gt;they are the popular .zip format under the hood&lt;/strong&gt;. Some files which, quite surprisingly, are actually archives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;popular formats used by Microsoft Word (&lt;em&gt;.docx&lt;/em&gt;), Excel (&lt;em&gt;.xlsx&lt;/em&gt;) and PowerPoint (&lt;em&gt;.pptx&lt;/em&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;their LibreOffice equivalents (&lt;em&gt;.odt&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;.odf&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;.odp&lt;/em&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;applications for Android phones (&lt;em&gt;.apk&lt;/em&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and, of course, translation packages (&lt;em&gt;.xlz&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;.mqxlz&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;.sdlppx&lt;/em&gt;…).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike XML files, archives can’t simply be viewed in your text editor. They contain compressed streams of data, which the text editor would try to directly convert into characters. This is what happens if you try to open an archive in Notepad:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost1/archive_mangled_in_notepad.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the text is mangled and unreadable. The only readable text within the raw bytes are file names, such as the name of the single file I zipped in this case - &lt;em&gt;example_file.txt&lt;/em&gt;, from line 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when browsing files in Windows Explorer or other file explorers, you can click on a &lt;em&gt;.zip&lt;/em&gt; file and see its contents as if it were a normal folder. This is because &lt;strong&gt;your operating system hides the complexity from you and unpacks the archive behind the scenes&lt;/strong&gt; (both Linux Mint and Windows 10 do it, from my experience).&lt;br /&gt;
However, if you tried to open and edit the files without extracting them first, you could encounter trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate, I saved this blog post to my disk, choosing the &lt;em&gt;“Web Page, complete”&lt;/em&gt; option. As a result, I got:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &lt;em&gt;(…).html&lt;/em&gt; file,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &lt;em&gt;(…)_files&lt;/em&gt; folder right next to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I packed them both into a zip archive. I opened both the original website and the one inside the archive by clicking on the &lt;em&gt;.html&lt;/em&gt; files. They both opened in my browser. However, they looked different.&lt;br /&gt;
Here is a side-by-side comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/assets/blogpost1/zipfile_mangle_illustration.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my browser opened the file locked inside the archive, the image was not loaded and the text looked different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because the &lt;em&gt;.html&lt;/em&gt; file refers to some files from the folder next to it. &lt;strong&gt;Even though we see the contents of the archive in the file explorers, our browser cannot access them&lt;/strong&gt;. So it can’t e.g. load the stylesheets which dictate the look of the website. This is also why the text looks different - the browser cannot access formatting information, so it uses the default font.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example shows us that files inside an archive are not as accessible as outside of it. If you want to modify the files, you should decompress the archive, make your changes, and then re-compress the bundle again. This is also what your CAT tools do behind the scenes every time they open a package - there is no magic here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, archive files used by translators usually contain a bunch of XML files: bilingual files for translation, structure of the source file (or the file itself), translation memories, glossaries… They might also contain some other reference files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-rules-of-thumb-for-dealing-with-files&quot;&gt;Some rules of thumb for dealing with files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the variety of file formats may seem daunting at first, they actually belong to a rather small set of categories and are subject to some universal rules.&lt;br /&gt;
Here are the ones which made it much easier for me to feel comfortable around files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Files are just blocks of bytes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, this means that two exactly identical files, opened by the same reliable software, will &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; appear exactly the same. In theory, you could write any file by hand. Sure, manual editing might be tedious and error-prone, but there is no magic in CAT tools which would force you to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Files of the same type can be processed in the same way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If it walks like a duck and it quacks like a duck, then it must be a duck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many file formats, but the number of actual standards is much lower - many files have a common stem. For this reason, all valid XML files can be parsed with an XML parser and all ZIP archives can be unzipped. Can’t find any search results for some obscure .xyz format? Solution: recognize that .xyz is actually XML, use proven tools to parse the file and then adapt them to your use-case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. File extensions are just a hint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manually change the extension of a file, you might see a warning pop up (on Windows) and the file icon change. This might make you think that the file was somehow converted. However, it wasn’t. The name of the file, including the extension, is &lt;strong&gt;separate from its content&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Some programs use custom file extensions to get distinct icons and treatment. But if their content is e.g. valid XML, then they can be opened perfectly fine as XML. Then point 2 applies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. There are exceptions to all rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how I write &lt;em&gt;reliable software&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;valid XML&lt;/em&gt;? Although the rules are universal, it’s always possible to encounter something atypical or plain buggy. Don’t let this discourage you from experimenting with file manipulation… but maybe don’t do it right before a deadline! 😀 Having a plan B always helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this clarifies things a bit and gives you some confidence. CAT tool formats really are more accessible than they seem. Let’s &lt;a href=&quot;/modern_translation_blog/jekyll/update/2020/08/16/translation-formats-practice.html&quot;&gt;apply our knowledge in real-life situations&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-resources&quot;&gt;Other resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3schools.com/xml/&quot;&gt;XML tutorial from W3C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zaac.de/pdf/2015_TLC_Warsaw_Zerfass_DataTransfer_with_tmx_tbx_and_xliff.pdf&quot;&gt;A presentation by Angelika Zerfass discussing &lt;em&gt;.tmx&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;.tbx&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;.xliff&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_archive_formats#Comparison&quot;&gt;Wikipedia’s summary of various archive formats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a series of blog posts on file formats used by CAT (Computer-assisted translation) programs for storing translation data. Their aim is to share some knowledge which should allow us to tame our CAT tools better. Or to become independent from their whims.</summary></entry></feed>